Welcome back to the channel, y'all.
Today, we're going to answer one very
important question. Is the Battlemaster
still the best subclass for the fighter?
Does this pristine build still hold up
even after the final patch? Well, grab
yourself a tall ale and uh let's find
out.
Now, before we get too far into the
video, we like to make thematic builds
on this channel. not necessarily trying
to stick to like a meta or being super
optimized, but the builds will work on
honor and tactician mode. And we try to
aim for a laid-back almost like
conversational tone. So, if that sounds
like your sort of vibe, consider hitting
that like and subscribe button and let's
get started. Now, like every epic tale
or journey, it all starts at the
character creation screen. And
naturally, we're going with a human. But
really, your your race, your background,
those are entirely all up to you. But
the class that we're going with is the
fighter. And at level one, we pick up
second wind, which is a nice use of our
bonus action for a little bit of
healing. Up next, we do get to pick a
fighting style. I just always go with
defense here. It's just kind of
universally really good. Uh, but also
great weapon fighting. This is really
handy, too. And then moving on to our
abilities. This is kind of the ability
layout I would have. High strength, high
dexterity, so we're higher up in the
turn order. And our constitution at 14,
and then our wisdom at 12. You could
flip-flop the constitution and dexterity
if you want, but as a fighter, we
already have access to heavy armor, and
we're proficient with constitution as
well. And just a quick note, if you're
looking at that strength and you're
like, um, you could just use elixirs of
hill giant strength, you could, but for
this video, we're going to assume that
you're not stashing up on those elixirs.
But yes, strength is very easy to
manipulate in Balders's Gate 3. Now,
let's move on to the leveling section.
First up at level two, we just pick up
action surge, which is one of the best
skills in the game and makes fighter
here very desirable for multiclassing.
But in this video, this isn't a
multiclass choice for us. This is all
natural, baby. Let's move on to level
three. At level three, we get to pick
our subclass, and we're going with the
battle master, which is going to provide
us these battle maneuvers. Now, they're
going to use a superiority die. And the
superiority die, this is going to be our
resource. is going to come back on long
and short rest and this is going to add
a 1d8 to our maneuvers that do damage
and later on it'll be upgraded to a
1d10. So we get to pick three maneuvers
at first here. I would go with disarming
attack because you're going to go up
against a lot of humanoids so you can
take away their weapons. Don't forget to
pick them up though after you disarm
them if you don't kill them outright.
But this is going to get that 1d8 added
to our damage. And then I would go with
the menacing attack because this has the
potential to add that frighten effect to
our target and also again going to add
that 1d8. And the last one I would pick
here is repost. This is kind of going to
be a counter to any enemy that hits us
in melee range. This is going to cost
our reaction and use a superiority die,
but again you'll be striking back at a
melee target and getting a 1d8 added on
top of it. And at level four, we get to
pick up our first feat. Now, as a
fighter, we're going to have access to
choosing four feats if we don't
multiclass, but we're going to talk
about all the feet potentials, foot
potentials. No, you just all the feet
potential feet. Anyways, we're going to
talk about all the feats right now. So,
starting off, the most boring pick is
the ability improvement and just bumping
up your strength, but we're not going to
need to do that, I don't think. Uh,
alert. This is going to be a great
choice because it's going to give us
five to our initiative and we can't be
surprised. Very solid pick there. I also
like taking athlete if you want to make
your strength 17 and then topping it off
to 18 at this point because athlete here
will make us very mobile on the
battlefield when we use our jump as our
bonus action to just get around. Uh I
love this pick here. This is a really
good one. Great weapon master. This is
probably what I would take first. Not
because of the raw damage. It's going to
add 10 to our damage at the cost of
minus five to our attack rolls. But
whenever we critical or kill a target,
we can then use our bonus action to
swing again. So even if you don't have
the damage portion for this feat
toggled, that part of the feat will
still work. Now, one of the reasons I
wanted to update this build is because
taking magic initiate warlock is
probably something we want to do at
level six because we get to pick two
cantrips and the one I want to pick here
is booming blade. We also can take
Eldridge Blast as a range option, but
booming blade is definitely the one to
lock in. We also get our a choice for a
spell. And I would either take hellish
rebuke. This would kind of be like a
range option as a reaction to kind of
like counter. So similar to repost, but
that only works in melee range. Well,
hellish rebuke you can do at enemies
that hit you from range. So that's going
to be a good option. Uh you can also
take hex. Hex is probably what I'm going
to take in the gameplay section because
you can recast this as long as you
maintain concentration. But I would go
with one of these two choices. At level
eight, I would actually take Savage
Attacker. Now, this will reroll our
attacks, including our superiority die.
So, at level 10, our superiority die is
going to get bumped up to a 1d10. And
right now, it's a 1d6, but or it's a
1d8, but these will get rerolled with
savage attacker on top of our normal
weapon attack. So, we're just getting
the highest damage output simply by
r-rolling our damage and taking the
highest option. And then a couple last
feats I want to mention here. If you
want to take your battlem as more of
like your archer, taking sharpshooter in
the place of great weapon master going
to be your best choice there. Also, I
guess the last fe that I want to mention
here is heavy armor master. So, this
will decrease non-magical attacks by
three and add plus uh one to your
strength. This is really good for
negating a little bit more damage and
can be a fun pick if you want to be more
tanky. Now, at level five, we get extra
attack. This is crucial for all marshall
characters. we can move quickly on to
level six. Now, at level six, we get to
pick up our second feat. I already took
great weapon master, so this time
around, I'm going to take uh magic
initiate warlock, pick up booming blade,
eldrich blast, and I already mentioned
probably going to take hex for this
playthrough. And we can move on to level
seven. Now, at level seven, we pick up
another superiority die. And we get to
pick up two more maneuvers. I would take
trip attack. This has the potential of
making your target prone, so that can be
always good. If you want to lean more
towards being a tank and doing a little
bit of aggro, goating attack can be a
good choice for that. Uh, but also push
attack. If you want to have like a push
with your attack, obviously, uh, this
would be a good choice, too. I'm just
going to take goating attack. And we can
move on to level eight. At level eight,
we get to pick up our third feed. And
I'm going to take savage attacker here
because we are utilizing our superiority
die a lot. So, this is just going to
help out with our damage. And we can
move on to level 9. Now, at level 9, we
get the class feature indomitable. So,
this is going to help out with our
saving throw rolls. This is another
reason why I took hex for magic initiate
warlock because that concentration will
be rerolled if we're going to fail. So,
having a little bit of protection with
that is never a bad thing. At level 10
here, our superiority die gets bumped up
to that 1d10. We mentioned that earlier.
We also get to pick up two more
maneuvers. Now, we already have the
mandatory ones, so just kind of pick
whatever you want. I like rally from
time to time. Nice support ability. And
then I'll probably just take pushing
attack. And we can move on to level 11.
And at level 11, fighters just become
absolute monsters on the battlefield
because they get improved extra attack.
So no fluff, no spells, no potions of
speed. We get three attacks with our
action. This class feature here just
makes fighters so damn strong. It's a
small thing, but it has a huge impact.
And finally, at level 12, we have the
choice to pick up our last feat, but
this is honestly probably the best time
to talk about multiclassing when it
comes to battlem fighter. Now, a popular
pick would be something like war cleric
and then choosing uh war domain here and
that's for those war priest charges. But
honestly, with great weapon master and
our improved extra attack, our bonus
action is already going to be
weaponized. Now, another choice would be
warlock, but you'd have to undo the
magic initiate warlock because you'd
want to be picking up those effects here
and now. I don't think multiclassing
with battlem fighter is the best choice.
I would just stick the whole way as the
battlem. And for your last feed here,
I'll just take alert. And let's go to
the gameplay section. Now, moving on to
the gameplay section here. Let's quickly
look at our equipment. And you're going
to see that none of this is very
special. Uh most of this comes from act
two. Uh but some things are act three,
like the black guard greaves here, the
the sword, and then the bow as well. But
we're not going to be using any rings or
amulets. And that's because the build
I'm showing off here, it's a it's a
framework. It's a baseline and you're
going to see that it works completely
fine with gear that I would say is on
par, maybe even like a little bit below
of what kind of gear you're going to
have at this point in the game. So,
obviously, yes, more better gear is
going to make this build even stronger
cuz it's not like I don't have any gear
at this point. You know, I have Nulna
here. I have something like the Halbert
of Vigilance, which is really good. And
then ring-wise, we're not going to be
wearing any rings, but I have rings that
are I think would be fitting for this
build or making it even better. Uh, and
because we took warlock initiate, this
amulet here can restore a spell slot.
They really, if your your spellcasters
are fine on uh their their spell
economy, then maybe give this to
something like a fighter like this. But
not really a top priority. I would give
them something like the amulet of the
harpers or even the amulet of misty
step. Give them a little bit more
ability. But again, gear-wise, not a big
deal. You'll have better stuff at this
point, or at least as good as this. Now,
for the gameplay section, we did a
little bit of uh breaking and entering,
and we're going to be soloing this steel
watch here. Now, we're going to do two
fights in this video. So, for this first
fight here, we're not going to use any
of these elixirs, but for the second
fight against multiple targets, we are
going to pop one of these elixirs, and
that's really just to speed it along.
But again, this guy here, it's going to
be all natural. And actually, you know
what? I lied. I am going to use the
elixir of hill giant strength because
that steel watch, that sword is pretty
heavy. And I don't think 18 strength or
16 strength is enough. So, uh, let's go
ahead and pop that and make sure we
don't run into that blunder. But anywh
who, let's go ahead and exit turn-based
mode and let's see who gets the first
uh, initiative role. Who or who's first
in the initiative role, I should say.
Let's go ahead and attack
>> 11 and eight. Nice. You love to see it.
Now, our movement not that great. That's
why something like Crusher's ring or the
amulet of missy step pretty good for a
build like this. Uh, but actually not
not a big deal in general because as a
battlemaster, we can also use our bow to
basically do the same thing that we're
going to be doing in melee range. So now
it's just a choice of what do I want to
do to him first? We could disarm him,
but we're not close enough to go pick it
up. I think actually we'll just hit him
with hex. I think I'll just choose
dexterity hex. I don't think it really
matters because it's a check, not a
saving throw. And then we'll go ahead
and just we'll just hit him with the
bow. And then we'll just wait till he
gets close to us. We'll get rid of luck
of the far realms or we'll we'll use it
up there so it doesn't keep procking for
us. We'll just whittle him down a little
bit and hit him one more time. Oh, he's
already lost a good chunk of health and
we haven't even done anything yet. All
right, end our turn. He's going to come
to us.
You missed. All right, now we're in
melee range here. Let's turn off our um
great weapon all in so that way we have
the highest percent chance of hitting
him. And when we hit him, we're going to
have a chance to disarm him. So, we
disarmed them there. Anytime you disarm
a target, even if you think you're going
to kill them, just go ahead and pick up
their weapon. Ow, that was rude. I was
talking there, brother. Um, but pick up
their weapon. And then now this steel
watch, he's going to do not as much
damage. And his melee range is not as
good either. Now, let's go ahead and
reactivate our great weapon all in. And
let's just go to town on him. And we
could just hit him with menacing strike
here just to do that extra uh 1d10
damage.
Even though this guy is immune to being
frightened, we'll go ahead and use our
action surge. And oh, he might be dead
this turn if we keep hitting him.
Well, one more for the money. All right,
he's done. Damn, that was uh it's a lot
quicker than I thought it was going to
be. Oh no. Are we going to get hit by
this?
We're okay. Easy easy as pie right
there. All right, now looks like we got
ourselves into a cave with a bunch of
these sea ladies here. Hey, what y'all
up to? What's some Oh, forbidden.
Nothing's off limits to me. I'm the hero
of the story. All right, starting a
fight against all of these uh water
people. I really don't remember what to
call them here. Um now, something we
didn't show off against the steel
watches. O, we got booming blade here.
And I didn't think it was really
necessary against the steel watch cuz we
were going to absolutely obliterate
them. But against these uh this group
here, let's just go ahead and start
going to town. Beautiful. And now we can
only do um booming blade once per action
which synergizes beautifully with action
surge here. So we'll be able to use
booming blade twice as long as we have
action surge up which comes back on
short rest. Uh but let's just go ahead
and finish her off. We'll go with uh
frighten instead or menacing attack.
Now they don't have much health left so
let's go ahead and start doing damage on
her over here. Bonk. She dropped her
weapon. Go ahead and pick that up. Get
an attack on me. That's fine. All right.
And now we're going to use our action
surge. We're going to use booming blade
on her.
Finish her off. Miss. That's okay.
Now, for a remaining turn, we could We
don't really need to heal. And rally is
only good for bolstering your allies.
You can't target yourself with it. Um,
so we'll just reapply Hex, actually. and
we'll target we'll target her over there
and then we'll end our turn and we'll
we'll see what they're going to do.
Probably not too happy that I just broke
in here. The [__] queen will end you.
Okay, sure. We'll see. We will see.
That's right. Come into the mix. Come
get a taste.
Couple water elementals. They're not
going to save you.
Although they do hurt a lot. I'll give
you that. That hurt a bit. All right, so
let's go ahead. And we just need to
start taking them out systematically
here. We'll strike her first.
Bonk. Great. Great hit there. That was
nasty. Let's go ahead and see if this
kills her. Nice.
Got another target here. Let's hit him
with trip attack.
Because if trip attack, if this
succeeds, we will then have advantage on
our next hit. But that's our turn there.
And next turn, we should be able to
basically finish them off.
Great. Create water. Just Just what my
character need to be a little wet.
>> None of them none of them did anything
to attack me on on their turns. They're
just they're not exactly the brightest,
but that's okay. We're going to booming
blade so we get the most damage on this
one here. Almost almost got them there.
Just do a regular attack now. Finish
them off with a regular attack. Okay,
you're going to survive. All right,
then. Well, I'll just We'll use our
bonus action.
Just a lot of swings and then and then
it became a one v one and I have a
feeling who's going to come out on top.
Although I do like your dress. A repost
baby. Yes. I love repost. It's so
awesome. See you.
I kind of want Booming Blade to take
them out. Let's see if they actually try
to run away.
Trying to make me look like a fool at
the end here, but that's okay. Ah, ah,
this was a this was a nice cleanup here,
but we still we weren't in time to save
our our fish friend here. Rest in peace,
brother. Rest in peace. All right,
y'all. That's the build. That's the
video. As you can see, Battlemaster
still [__] rocks. Now, there are some
items that make Battlem even better.
Specifically, Gauntlets of the Warm
Master. It'll it'll impose disadvantage
on the saving throws for when you're
using your battle maneuvers. So, if you
were sitting there thinking, man, he's
using disarm and uh that trip attack and
it's not procking that often, use those
gloves and that'll help that out a lot.
But overall, man, Battlemaster such a
great frontliner. Hell, even if you
don't want to use it as a frontliner,
you could use it as an archer and use
all your maneuvers at range instead. And
such a such a well-rounded subclass
overall. Now, how does it compete
against Arcane Archer? Well, we're going
to have to shove that discussion for a
versus series, and I think the next one
will be fighter. So, I will see you guys
then. Peace and take care.
[Music]